Guide to the Social Ethics Pamphlet Collection
Yale University Divinity School Library
Social Ethics Pamphlet Collection
1919-1972
1938-1958
RG 73
Yale University Divinity School Library
52
(131 boxes)
The Collection includes pamphlets, brochures, typescripts, booklets, comic books, posters, cartoons, letters, memoranda, offprints, etc., documenting various aspects of social issues in America and throughout the world during the mid-twentieth century.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Liston Pope
Custodial History
These materials were collected or created during the period 1938-1973 by Liston C. Pope, Dean and Professor of Social Ethics at the Yale Divinity School, and his students.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
Pope's 1938 introductory course in Social Ethics was described as follows in the Bulletin of Yale University Divinity School: "... an examination, in the light of sociological facts, of contemporary problems of industry, race, property distribution, the family, etc., and a consideration of the social and ethical implications of various forms of economic and political organization. Secular proposals for social reconstruction [are] investigated, and particular attention devoted to the relevance of the Christian ethic to the social order."
In this course, and in others such as "Contemporary Social Systems", "The Church and Social Classes", "The Church and Labor", and "Christianity and Communism", Pope and his students addressed social issues from both descriptive and analytic perspectives, engaging topical areas both as discrete societal issues and events, and as wide-ranging phenomena impacting the character of American society. Pope systematically collected primary source materials from hundreds of different organizations and on many different topics to support his teaching - materials as wide ranging as daily newspapers from World War II relocation camps for Japanese-Americans, virulent antisemitic propaganda, a comic book depicting America's possible fate under Communism, and literature for and against the National Health Insurance program proposed by President Truman in 1948.
Scope and Contents
The Social Ethics Pamphlet Collection is divided into three series:
I. Corporate Bodies
II. Topical Files
III. Student Papers
The subject areas most extensively documented by the Collection are as follows:
Race relations: The majority of the material related to race relations deals with the relationship between African Americans and white Americans, but there are also significant holdings that address antisemitic, anti-Asian, and anti-immigrant sentiments in American society.
Communism and subversive activity: A notable group of materials pertains to the use of the Communist threat as a tool by political and industrial interests to discredit the labor and civil rights movements. The potency of the Communist threat in the public mind is well documented.
Labor and industrial relations: Significant materials document the growing labor movement of the 1930s and 1940s as well as the political response of industry; the propaganda war between labor and industry is well documented. The collection reveals Pope's particular interest in labor relations in terms of issues of economic justice and enfranchisement.
Ecumenical and individual church organizations: Materials representative of numerous Protestant denominations and Catholic Church agencies provide a profile of movement toward church cooperation during this era, and the engagement of the Christian community with social issues. The most extensive holdings are from the Congregational Christian Churches and the United Church of Christ. Beyond printed material related to social issues, there is also significant documentation of the ecclesiastical battle surrounding the merger of the Congregational Christian Churches and Evangelical and Reformed Church, forming the United Church of Christ.
Judaism, Israel-Arab conflicts, Jews in America: There are four areas of emphasis within this subject category: 1) the relations between the Jewish and Christian communities in America, 2) the American Jewish labor movement, 3) Jewish life in America (particularly the activities of Hillel and B'nai Brith), and 4) the Zionist movement and the inception of the state of Israel. Some documentation relating to the Holocaust is available amidst materials relating to European war refugees and international relief.
World War, 1939-1945: The focus of these materials is not the military aspects of the conflict, but rather the societal and human costs of the war. Efforts to assist refugees and provide economic relief to war areas are documented. Peace movements in the U.S., primarily before 1942, are also documented.
In addition to these broad subject areas, there is also significant documentation related to specific societal phenomena such as agriculture and rural life, alcoholism, birth control, cooperative societies, mental health and medical care
Series I, Corporate Bodies, includes material from more than one thousand different organizations representing all points on the political and religious spectra. A sample entry, below, indicates the categories utilized to describe material contained in this series:
Corporate body: Committee Against Jim Crow in Military Service
Geographical location: New York, NY [headquarters of organization]
Inclusive dates: 1948 [i.e. publication dates]
Subjects: Race relations; Armed Forces [Library of Congress subject headings]
Name changes, etc.: [includes pseudonyms]
Physical location: Box 9 Folder 8
Summary: Contains typescript "Memorandum of inquiry into the effect of discrimination and segregation on the morale and development of Negro soldiers."
Series II, Topical Files, also includes some documentation from corporate bodies, but these files have been kept in their original, topically arranged, format. The topics covered in this material include:
Academic freedom
Africa
African Americans
Aged
Agriculture
Alcoholism
American periodicals
Anti-Catholicism
Antisemitism
Armed Forces
Arts and Society
Birth control
Broadcasting
Catholic Church--apologetic works
Catholic Church--controversial works
Child care
Children
Christian communities
Christian education
Church and social problems
Church and the world
Church work with students
City missions
Civil rights
College students
Communism
Community organization
Conscientious objectors
Conservatism
Cooperative societies
Correctional institutions
Crime
Drug abuse
Economic policy
Ecumenical movement
Education
Evangelicalism
Environmental protection
Family
Fascism
Freedom of religion
Gambling
Hispanic Americans
Homosexuality
Immigrants
Indians of North America
International organization
International relations
International relief
Israel-Arab conflicts
Japanese-Americans
Jews
Judaism--relations--Christianity
Juvenile delinquency
Korean War, 1950-1953
Labor movement
Law
Marriage
Migrant labor
Medical care
Medical ethics
Mental health
Missions to Jews
Nativism
Nuclear disarmament
Peace movements
Poverty
Propaganda
Prostitution
Protest movements
Public housing
Race relations
Radicalism
Refugees
Religion and culture
Religion and international affairs
Religion and politics
Rural conditions
Science--Moral and ethical aspects
Sects
Sino-Japanese conflict--1937-1945
Social legislation
Southern States
Subversive activities
United States--politics and government
United States--social conditions--1933-1945
Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975
Women
World politics
World War, 1939-1945
Youth
Zionism
There is extensive documentation in this series of the "us" versus "them" mentality in American society during this era, in all its various manifestations. Material in this series can be linked with related materials in Series I through subject heading searches.
Series III, Student Papers, contains 143 typescript term papers prepared by Yale Divinity School students. Prof. Pope encouraged his students to collect primary documents and conduct survey and interviews in connection with their research for these papers. This collected data is of objective value, even beyond the students' interpretation of it, and in many cases samples of primary source material are included with the paper.
Arrangement
I. Corporate Bodies
II. Topical Files
III. Student Papers
Agriculture; Alcoholism; Arab-Israeli conflict; Birth control; Church and social problems; Communism; Cooperative societies; Ecumenical movement; Immigrants; Jews; Judaism -- Relations -- Christianity; Labor movement; Medical care; Mental health; Race relations; Rural conditions; Subversive activities; World War, 1939-1945; Pope, Liston, 1909-1974
- Corporate Bodies, Series I
  - A
    - AFL-CIO, 1942-1965 (Box 39, Folder 1-3)
      Scope and Contents
      Geographical location: Washington, DC
      Subjects: Labor movement; Race relations; Religion and culture
      Name changes etc.: American Federation of Labor - Congress of Industrial Organizations
      Comments: contains pamphlets about the organization's position on civil rights and urban renewal, and two issues of the I.U.D. Digest; see box 109 for extensive collection of the IUD Bulletin; pamphlets on benefits won by the union; proposed "right to work" legislation; address given by Sen. John F. Kennedy at 1957 union convention.
    - AFL-CIO (CIO-Committee to Abolish Discrimination), 1942, 1947 (Box 39, Folder 4)
      Subjects: Labor movement; Race relations
      Comments: contains two pamphlets issued by the committee
    - AFL-CIO (CIO-Department of Education and Research) (Box 39, Folder 5)
      Subjects: Labor movement
      Comments: contains issues of newsletter: Economic outlook, speech by Kermit Eby on U.S. foreign and domestic policy, and pamphlets on union activities
    - AFL-CIO (CIO-Legislative Department), 1954 (Box 39, Folder 6)
      Subjects: Economic policy
      Comments: contains papers on a proposed 1954 change to the Federal Tax Code
    - AFL-CIO (CIO-National Citizen's Political Action Committee), 1944-1952 (Box 39, Folder 7)
      Geographical location: New York, NY
      Subjects: Labor movement; United States--politics and government
      Comments: contains issues of newsletter: Political Guide, and other papers concerning legislative and election issues
    - AFL-CIO (CIO-National Community Services Committee), n.d. (Box 39, Folder 8)
      Subjects: Community organization; Labor movement
      Comments: contains pamphlets about union involvement in community organizations
    - AFL-CIO (CIO-Religious Associates of the National Citizen's Action Committee), 1945 (Box 39, Folder 9)
      Subjects: Labor movement; Religion and culture
      Comments: contains papers on the union's work with religious organizations
    - AFL-CIO--Industrial Union Department, 1956-1962 (Box 109)
      Comments: contains extensive collection of the IUD Bulletin; for related materials see files 39-1 & 1a
    - Adult Education Association, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Geographical location: Chicago, IL
      Subjects: Community organization; Education
      Comments: Contains two pamphlets: "How to teach adults" (1955) and "Taking action in the community" (1955).
    - Advertising Council, 1952-1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Subjects: Economic policy; Religion and culture--United States; Capitalism.
      Name changes etc.: American Round Table
      Comments: The Council--"a non-profit, non-partisan business organization which serves the public interest by marshaling the forces of advertising to promote voluntary, individual actions in solving national problems"--sponsors the American Round Table. Contains "Anti-Americanism and the people's capitalism movement," by Theodore S. Repplier (1957); three "American Round Table discussions: "The moral and religious basis of the American society" (1952); "Discussions on people's capitalism," by David M. Potter (1956); and "Moral attitudes and will to achievement of Americans," by Harold Rosenberg (1961).
    - Alabama Council on Human Relations, Inc., 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Geographical location: Birmingham, AL
      Subjects: Race relations
      Name changes etc.: Published "Alabama Council Newsletter"
      Comments: The Council is "an independent, non-profit organization seeking to improve social conditions in Alabama through research and Education;" Contains four issues of "Newsletter" (1958-62); "The Positive Approach" [address by Marion A. Wright on the struggle for equal rights] (1961).
    - Allied Church League, Inc., 1950 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Geographical location: Shelby, NC
      Subjects: Alcoholism
      Comments: The League's slogan is "That which is morally wrong cannot be economically or politically right." Contains single issue of "To-morrow" (1950).
    - Allied Forces, Inc., [n.d.] (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Geographical location: Rochester, NY
      Name changes etc.: Operates "Scientific Alcohol Education" program.
      Comments: Allied Forces' purpose is to (1) "publicize studies...on the relation of alcohol to health, emotional stability, [etc.]; (2) facilitate and stimulate...the promotion of scientific alcohol education; and (3) cooperate with...organisations ...to supplement their programs with information, services, leadership training, and teaching." Contains untitled pamphlet on the Scientific Alcohol Education program's purpose [n.d.]; "Supplementary teaching in scientific alcohol education in high school classes" [n.d.].
    - Allied Youth, Inc., [1953-1960] (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Comments: Allied Youth stands for "the liberation through education of the individual and society from the handicaps of beverage alcohol." Contains "Manual of Allied Youth" [n.d.]; pamphlet advertising book "John Barleycorn: His life and letters," by Dan Poling [n.d.]; "Is this it?" by Dan Poling [n.d.].; "For young people only," by Grace Nies Fletcher [n.d.]; two issues of "The Allied Youth" (1957, 1960); "Allied Youth" [n.d.] and cover letter (1953); six press releases (1953-54).
    - American Afro-Asian Educational Exchange, Inc., [1964-1967?] (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Subjects: Communism; China.
      Comments: The Exchange is "a non-profit educational foundation...to further better understanding among the peoples of Africa, Asia and the United States ...to strengthen the cause of international freedom threatened by Communism;" Contains "Appeasement: Another setback," by Wei Tao-ming [1967?]; "The shattered illusion: African students in communist countries" [n.d.]; "Communist China and the non-committed countries: Motives and purposes of communist China's foreign policy," by Franz Michael [1964?].
    - American Arbitration Association, 1940-1946 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Comments: The Association "has established, maintains and administers a national system of Commercial Arbitration Tribunals for the voluntary arbitration of civil and commercial controversies." Contains "Commercial arbitration tribunals" [c1941]; pamphlet advertising "Arbitration in Action" [new monthly journal on arbitration] [1942?]; "Annual report for 1940" [1941?]; "Code of ethics for arbitrators: Some basic principles of right conduct" (reprinted from "The Arbitration Journal" [1946]); and "a poll of final results of the tally".
    - American Association for Better Dental Health, [1944-1945] (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Subjects: Medical care
      Name changes etc.: American Association for Dental Health
      Comments: Contains "Statement to the sponsors of the declaration of principles" [in re a proposed method for financing dental care in an experimental group clinic], by Charles L. Hyser, DMD (1944); letter to "Friend and sponsor," by John Oppie McCall, DDS (1944); letter to "Friend and sponsor," by John Oppie McCall, DDS (1945); "Committee of sponsors" [n.d.].; "Committee of sponsors Classified" [n.d.].
    - American Association for Economic Freedom, [1939]-[1940] (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Comments: The Association is "an educational, non-profit organization" whose object is "to undertake studies and surveys of economic, industrial, and political subjects and problems, to promote discusssion thereof in college and other public forums, and to make available reports of such studies, surveys, and discussions." Contains "Democracy and economic planning: Statement for the Interfaith Conference signed by leading Protestant, Catholic and Jewish clergymen" [1939]; two copies of "Can unemployment be ended?" by John A. Ryan, D.D. (1940).
    - American Association for a Democratic Germany, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10a)
      Geographical location: unidentified
      Subjects: International relations; Germany
      Comments: Goal:"to foster the development of genuine democracy in Germany". Numerous prominent religious leaders on National Committee of AADG, including Reinhold Niebuhr, G. Bromley Oxnam, Henry P. Van Dusen. Sponsored the Council for a Democratic Germany, headed by Paul Tillich.
    - American Association for the United Nations, Inc., 1945 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Subjects: Peace movements; Nuclear disarmament
      Name changes etc.: Formerly known as the Commission to Study the Organization of Peace (file 45-1)
      Comments: Contains two copies of news release "Control of atomic energy" (1945).
    - American Association of Personal Finance Companies, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Subjects: Economic policy; Social legislation
      Comments: Contains "Combining forces for social betterment: a collection of papers which shed light on problems for which straight thinkers in business and welfare work are seeking solutions" (1940). The pamphlet consists of "a selected group of papers by men...identified with social welfare activities, institutions of learning, legal aid societies and the personal finance business," which were first published in either "Personal Finance News" or "The Annals" of the American Academy of Political and Social Science.
    - American Association of School Administrators, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Comments: Contains "From sea to shining sea - Administrators handbook for intergroup education".
    - American Association of Teachers Colleges, [1946] (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Geographical location: [Oneonta, NY]
      Comments: Contains "Teaching teachers cooperative action" (reprinted from the twenty-fifth yearbook of the American Association of Teachers Colleges 1946).
    - American Birth Control League, Inc., 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Subjects: Birth control
      Comments: Contains "Medical opinion on birth control" [issued jointly by the League and the Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau] (1938); "American medicine accepts birth control" (reprinted from "Birth Control Review" [1937]).
    - American Business Consultants, Inc., 1947 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Subjects: Communism
      Comments: Contains one issue of "Counterattack" (the newsletter of facts on communism).
    - American Christian Palestine Committee, 1949-1960 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Subjects: Jews; Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945); Israel-Arab conflicts; Palestine
      Comments: Contains four issues of "Land Reborn" (1953-60); "Arab and Jewish refugees--Problems and prospect" by Karl Baehr [1953?]; "Answers on the Palestine question" by Carl Hermann Voss (1949); "Report by Christian fact-finding mission on Jerusalem rejects internationalization plan after investigation there" (1950); "Memorandum on Yusif El-Bandak" [Christian Arab who favors the internationalization of Jerusalem] (1949); draft of letter to President Truman on the future status of Jerusalem (1949); "Jerusalem and the Christian world: A Letter to the President of the United States" (1949); "Club program service" [directory of "speakers who can authoritatively discuss...Israel"] [n.d.]; "The holy places--A Catholic view" (1949); reprint of a letter about Arab refugees to the editor of "The Presbyterian Tribune" (1949); "The Arabs and Israel," by Karl Baehr (1949).
    - American Civil Liberties Union, 1941-1956 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Subjects: Civil rights
      Name changes etc.: ACLU
      Comments: The ACLU is "the only permanent national non-partisan organization devoted solely to defending the Bill of Rights for everybody"; it "fights for the civil liberties even of those whose anti-democratic opinions it abhors." Contains "Strong in their pride and free" [excerpts from speech on the Federal Security Program] by Harry P. Cain (1955); "The Bill of Rights" (1956); "Sedition!" [re the federal indictment of 29 alleged members of the Socialist Workers Party at Minneapolis charged with advocating force and violence to overthrow the government and incitement to disaffection in military forces] (1941); "Academic freedom and academic responsibility" (1956); annual reports (1951-56); "Democracy in trade unions - a survey, with a program of action" (1943); "Academic freedom and academic responsibility" (1952); and two untitled publicities.
    - American Committee for Christian German Refugees, 1938-1940 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Subjects: Refugees; World War, 1939-1945; Germany
      Name changes etc.: American Committee for Christian Refugees
      Comments: The Committee's function is "to assist Protestant Christians of all denominations who, because of economic, political or religious changes in Germany and Austria, are obliged to seek citizenship and livelihood in other countries." Contains "Government of the people... Brotherhood of Christians...." [n.d.]; "But now--An outcast" [1938?]; "Refugee immigration: Facts and figures" [1939?]; untitled pamphlet on refugees [1940?]; solicitation letters from New Haven Committee for Christian Refugees (1940); reprint of "Job peril denied: Refugees not menace to U.S." by Ernest L. Meyer, from "New York Post" (1940); single issue of "Common Cause" (1939); "Modern Christian German martyrs" [n.d.].
    - American Committee for Cultural Freedom, [n.d.] (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Comments: Contains "We put freedom first" [begins with premise that "intellectual freedom is one of the inalienable rights of man"] [n.d.].
    - American Committee for Non-Participation in Japanese Aggression, ca. 1938 (Box 2, Folder 1A)
      Subjects: International relations; Sino-Japanese Conflict--1937-1945
      Comments: Pamphlet: "America's Share in Japan's War Guilt"
    - American Committee for Protection of Foreign Born, 1939-1948 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Subjects: Civil rights; Immigrants
      Comments: The Committee is "an independent, non-partisan organization devoted to (1) increased participation by the foreign born in the political life of the nation; (2) the exposure and routing of fifth column and anti-democratic elements in the foreign born community; (3) the elimination of all discrimination because of race or national origin in the naturalization and immigration laws, in production and in all phases of our national life; and (4) the defeat of all 'anti-alien' bills in Congress, and the passage of legislation to facilitate and encourage the naturalization of non-citizens." Contains "The Supreme Court on the Bridges case" and "Concurring opinion of Justice Frank Murphy" (1945); "The social and economic consequences of Exclusionary immigration laws," by Felix S. Cohen (1939); "A Death -Trap for democracy" [n.d.]; "Concentration camps threaten all Americans" [n.d.]; "Review of the year 1948"; "The Registration of Aliens," by Vito Marcantonio (1940); "An open letter to President
    - American Committee in Aid of Chinese Industrial Cooperatives, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Subjects: Economic policy; China.
      Name changes etc.: Indusco, Inc.
      Comments: Contains single issue of "Indusco Bulletin" (1946); solicitation letter for Bailie School treasure chest drive (1946).
    - American Committee on Africa, Inc., 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Geographical location: New York, NY; Washington, DC
      Subjects: International relations; Africa